Heat. Heat.
[Music]
Hello, good evening, good day everybody
and welcome to the Ask Abijit Show
episode 273. I hope everyone's doing
great. Let us see who all is there in
the live chat. So this is going to be a
super chat and live chat uh episode. I'm
going to take questions live from all of
you and you can start asking but let me
see who all is there on the live chat. I
can see meet Arian Patel Sagar Toat
Manish Khar Do Suas
Suas Ready Rashmir from Rajasthan.
Bageshwar Army Samana Satish
uh Ramshukla Shri Ramchandra Anamaha
Hitan Shua Sep Raj Krishnagiri Savary
Set from Bihar from planet Bihar. Uh
Sumit again geopolitical dub from Indor
Pay Paul from Kolkata. Who else do we
have? Shrea Smithra from Moscow. Jay Gum
Boswis Djamat says good morning. Well,
good morning to you sir. Nishant Tari
Latangi Suresh Alvin Rodriguez Animesh
Paul Aush Somi Jane from Jaipur Anub
Namaste Shiv Watza Meit. Who else do we
have? We have Suas. We have Ashwari
Nagar.
We have pro gamer Om and lots and lots
of other people. So hello everybody and
great to see you all. Now let's get
going with some questions. More people
are chiming in. Alan Jay Victor,
Uncle Bag Packer from Pune, Atangi Sur
from Tamil Nadu. Good morning. Well,
good morning and everybody else. Okay,
let's get get going some with some
questions. We have one super chat right
now. So let's take that. Rohan Sunea
says, "Should India take over the Atolla
island given its strategic location near
Pakistan's coast?
If the UK can hold the Faulland Islands
from 12,000 kilometers away, why can't
we? So, to answer that question, first
of all, let's take a look at where this
island is located. Uh, let's go to the
map. I'm going to put the map on the
screen, and we're going to go and find
this island, Ashola Island. So, Aola
Island is off the coast of Pakistan.
Uh, somewhere over here.
Now, where where will it be? Let's find
it. It's it it won't be very far away
from
from Guada. So I suppose this should be
Asta. Here we have it. So first of all,
let me click here. This is Atola Island.
And let's zoom out so that we understand
where we are talking, what location
we're talking about. It's not very far
from the coast of India. If we do a
straight line from Katch to Atolah, it's
about 470 something kilometers away.
Now this island belongs to Pakistan.
This is officially Pakistani territory.
This is not disputed territory unless
you consider the whole of Pakistan to be
disputed territory. So it's Pakistani
territory. Now according to
international law, you just you can't
just walk in and take over someone's
territory,
right? You can't do that unless there is
a just cause for that. And right now we
don't have a just cause for that. And if
we start go going and doing such things,
it will give other nations the the the
justification for trying to do something
similar to us. If the world starts
behaving in that manner that whoever is
stronger just goes and grabs whatever
they want, then the entire international
system collapses. Now you are comparing
this with the Faulland Islands. Let's
consider that as well. So the Faulland
Islands or the Malvas are located off
the coast of Argentina.
Okay, these are the islands and they
obviously are significantly far away
from the UK. Uh just a rough
measurement. If we do a straight line
measurement, it's going to be about
there we have it 12,000 something
kilometers.
But the fact is that these islands have
been held by the UK for a very long
time. they are off the coast of
Argentina which is why the um the
Argentine government the nation of
Argentina claims these islands as its
own
uh and there's history behind that we'll
not go into that uh but that's a
different case when it comes to island
we have see whoever was in charge of
making decisions
in the late 1940s 45 46 47 they decided
that India will be partitioned and
Indian territory will be given over to
create a new country artificial
temporary nation called Pakistan and
Atolah was part of that so you can't
just walk in there and take it I'm sure
we can do it we are powerful powerful
enough to go and take the island and and
retain it if we want to the Pakistanis
will put up some reg resistance but I'm
sure we can do this but the point is
that it is illegal according to
international law to just walk into
someone's territory and grab it Right.
We can but it it's going to cause all
kinds of problems for us. The more
powerful nations like the US and China
will then sanction India and declare
India as you know categorize India in
the same category as Russia for the
alleged Russian invasion of Ukraine
which obviously has happened right. So
we can do it but it is not advisable to
do that until and unless we become so
powerful that nobody can stop us. And
obviously Pakistan was created
artificially
without considering the sentiments of
the Indian people without having a
referendum as to whether the Indian
people are willing to give up Indian
territory to create this artificial
nation. That's a whole different story.
But what's happened has happened and
today Pakistan is a legally recognized
nation and according to international
law we just can't do that. Right? So I'm
sure it's strategically great and all
that but it it it's it's
not something we can do as of now. Okay,
let's take another question. This is by
Rashik Udin. Rashik Udin says, why are
there so many plane crashes this year?
So let's take a look at plane crash
statistics, shall we?
Uh let's let's remove this. Okay, the
question is why are there so many plane
crashes this year? Are there are there
more plane crashes this year compared to
other years? Let's find out. Uh let's go
and uh do a simple Google search. Number
of plane crashes per year.
Number of plane
crashes
per year. Let's see. Number of plane
crashes. Um where shall we go? I think
we can take a look at Wikipedia even
though it's not necessarily reliable,
but let's take a look. Plane crashes per
year history. What do we have?
Aviation. Okay, this doesn't seem to
have a yearby-year thing. So, let's not
go there. Let's uh let's move out. Do we
have
yearly statistics somewhere?
What does this AI overview say?
Fatal accidents blah blah blah rate. Um
not sure. Do we have some figures?
What is this? People killed. No, we just
want to know the number of air crash
accidents, not number of deaths.
Not sure. Not sure. Where do we find
something?
Okay, I'll have to look into this. This
is
per year. Do we have this?
How many commercial plane crashes per
year? Uh fatal accidents.
Okay. From from 2020 to 2025
2020 2025. Let's see.
Okay, let us see. What is panny flaw? I
don't know what it is, but let's take a
look. Do you have a yearby-year
breakdown? Once again, it's not giving.
Okay, maybe it does.
aviation crashes.
So, look, it looks like the number of
crashes per year is going down, but it
doesn't seem to have the latest 2025
statistics. Let me see over here. It's
only up to 2019 here. Okay, fine. We'll
have to go somewhere else, I suppose.
And somebody's asking the same question.
How many plane crashes this?
Uh, let us see. Two small planes, blah
blah, etc.
Okay, once again it's okay. Look, I'm
not going to do this because it's it's
going to take half an hour perhaps. The
point is that just because there is a
lot of media coverage of air crashes,
aircraft crashes, doesn't necessarily
mean that there are more more plane
crashes than than previous years this
year. It doesn't mean that. It doesn't
mean that at all. So, I don't know. I'll
have to go and look into the statistics
to figure out how many plane crashes
have occurred per year in the past 10
years or so. And then if we can find
that then perhaps we can um do we have
perplexity? Let me see. Perplexity.
Maybe Perplexity can f can find us. Um
okay, let's let's go to Perplexity and
check that out.
Okay, let's do this. Please list the
number number
of
plane crashes that occurred
per year
between 2015 and 25.
Let's see what perplexity they can find
us. What can it find? Um blah blah blah
etc. Okay, let's see. I don't want
fatalities, but it's still giving me
fatalities. So, 2015, 123, 2021, 113,
2022, 100.
Wow. Okay. 2025, we have 122. Well,
that's that's interesting. That's that's
rather concerning. Uh the average
I think even we just barely halfway
through 2025 and we already above the
average per year of the past 10 years.
Well, looks like what you are saying may
be true. So, it looks like there
actually are more plane crashes this
year than in previous years. Well,
that's interesting and that's
concerning. Why is it so? Is it because
safety standards have dropped in some
airline manufacturing
companies? Maybe. I don't know.
I think we we'll be able to figure out
what the reason is only in hindsight
only once the year is over and we can
analyze what's happening. One point of
concern is very clear that Boeing the
Boeing aircraft company now I could ask
perplexity to you know tell us
how many of these were Boeing aircraft
and how many were not. We could do that
also but I'll not do it right now. Um,
but it's possible. I mean, shall we do
that? Shall we do that? Let's do that.
Uh, let's ask a follow-up question. Um,
how many of the
uh plane crashes?
Plane
plane crashes
in 2025
involved
Boeing aircraft.
Let's see. We have 122 crashes this
year.
not explicitly summarized. It's trying
to hide.
Okay. Well, I'm sure it has the
statistics.
I suppose it's it's I think we'll have
to interrogate it further and use some
specific prompting techniques perhaps to
get the get to the bottom of this. There
is a there is an ongoing concern about
Boeing. Okay. Boeing has in the past few
years seemingly
lowered its uh safety standards
and they have tried to hide things from
the public. They there they had these
couple of plane crashes that happened
one in Indonesia and one in Ethiopia
that were because of the faulty MCAS
system I believe which was a software
patch that would force the aircraft's
nose to keep going down if the one of
the uh angle of attack sensors was
faulty and you usually have two angle of
attack sensors on both sides of the
fuselage but the MCAST system was tied
was connected only to one of these
sensors.
So a single point of failure which is
incredible and that that's what caused
the two crashes and after the first
crash happened Boeing was aware that
this is the the faulty MCCast system
that caused the crash and yet they hid
they suppressed this they hid this from
the public and they allowed a second
crash to happen. So there are concerns
about moving no question about it and uh
perplexity I think I'll have to
interrogate it using third or fourth
degree or something to to get the answer
but uh yeah looks like perplexity is not
very forthcoming with the answer. So
yeah there are issues with Boeing for
sure but I'm not sure if it's the the
entirety if if if that is the only
reason why there have been more more
plane crashes this year. We'll have to
look into it. Right now I don't have an
answer but one thing is very clear
Boeing is there are problem problems
with Boeing and all of that goes back to
uh the merger that Boeing had with the
McDonald Douglas company
uh which happened I think I don't know
quite a while ago but that's when the
the company's culture changed the it was
the McDonald Douglas bosses who
essentially eventually took over
operations in in Boeing and they changed
the culture of the company they they
they moved the headquarters from one
city, the long-standing city to another
city and everything changed in Boeing
and they started doing cost cutting and
it became a marketing marketing driven
company rather than an engineering
driven driven company and u yeah that's
that seems to be the reason why there
have been so many issues but we'll have
to see we'll have to see yeah
swastik mahesh thank you very much sir
thank you
Aries mantor says given the recent
sanctions imposed by imposed on India by
the European Union and China's seemingly
good behavior. How important is
aggressive leverage in negotiations?
Well, if you have ever negotiated for
anything, leverage is all that matters
in negotiations. Whether it's aggressive
or non-aggressive leverage, leverage is
leverage. Leverage doesn't have a type.
Leverage is leverage. The more leverage
is
leverage is a scalar quantity. It is not
it's not a vector quantity. Leverage has
magnitude. it doesn't have direction. So
the larger your leverage and the more
different kinds of leverage you have,
the better off you are in negotiations,
right?
So leverage is all that matters in
negotiations. If you have no leverage,
then you're going to come off second
best in in the negotiations and
obviously you need to know how to
negotiate. Yeah. So leverage is very
important. Yes. So recently the EU has
sanctioned an Indian refinery because of
uh because we are importing Russian
crude oil and then refining it and then
selling it to the EU nations and the EU
has imposed sanctions on that that
Indian company Indian refinery and let's
see how the government of India responds
to that. But yeah, so this is an ongoing
issue for us.
They're essentially trying to clamp down
on India's sovereignty on what we can do
and what we cannot do as a sovereign
nation. They will decide. So that that's
an issue.
Okay. Prrenit says
listen this is not a geopolitical
question sir. I have said it very
clearly. I'm going to take only
geopolitical questions today. I don't
deal in I don't look into national
politics. I'm very sorry but I I will
not be taking this question. I have put
a pinned comment that I'm going to take
geopolitical questions only. So why are
you doing this? I I don't understand. I
I'm sorry. I I don't discuss national
politics, internal politics. I just
don't do it. So there we have it.
Shivam says, "What's the update in
Burma?" I have no idea. Update of what
kind? Geopolitical update. It's it's an
ongoing situation. It's an ongoing
situation. The the nation is in a state
of civil war. Uh about half of the
nation is under the control of the uh
government of Burma, the military
government. And about half of the nation
is in the control of various ethnic
groups and the and the militias they
have formed. And all of these militias
obviously they are supported by foreign
nations. Generally there are two nations
that are supporting various militias.
One is the nation of China and one is
the United States. So it's a proxy war
that you're seeing in Burma.
And generally the militias that are
supported by the United States are
militias connected to ethnic groups that
have been converted to Christianity over
the past few decades or whatever.
Whichever ethnic groups are Christian,
they're fighting on behalf of the US and
whichever ethnic groups are
non-Christian, they're fighting for
China or they're fighting autonomously.
But autonomously if you're fighting, you
will not get your endless supply of arms
and ammunition. Right? You need arms and
ammunition. Even if you have AK-47s, you
need bullets. After firing a few, you're
going to get rid of the bullets will
you're going to exhaust your bullets,
right? So where do the bullets come
from? They can only come if you have a
foreign patron because you're not
manufacturing bullets at home, right? So
that's the deal. So it's an ongoing
situation and it has spilled over into
India and into Manipur mostly and that
is something the government of India
needs to look into. I mean, do we want
to absorb lacks of foreigners who have
no allegiance to our culture,
civilization or our country and who are
essentially proxies of of of uh the
United States? Do we want that? Is that
what we want to do? You want to give up
half of the territory of money of
Manipur to foreigners? I don't care how
many decades they've been squatting in
India. Pakistanis were recently
discovered who have been in India since
the 1950s and 1960s. doesn't mean
they're Indians now. So let's say these
cookies have been here since 1890. So
what? It doesn't make them Indian,
right? They they they've been
transplanted to create this artificial
problem.
They've been transplanted from from
various parts of Burma into Manipur to
punish the kingdom of Manipur. That's
what the British did. It was a punitive
measure to bring in foreigners who would
then create problems for the locals. Do
we want these people in India? Really?
So that's something the government of
India needs to look into and uh we have
to treat all foreigners all foreign
infiltrators and squatters in India the
same way no matter how many decades they
have been sitting in India it doesn't
matter even if they have documents
Aadhaar cards and PAN cards and god
knows what other cards they must have
been given we know what the deal is it's
very easy if you have local political
connections to get these documents
created and There'll be actual real
documents.
So many Rohingyas in Bangladeshes have
these Aadhaar cards and I don't know
election cards, election ID cards and
bank accounts and everything. It's
usually easier for these foreigners to
get documents compared to actual
Indians. So yeah, all all of this needs
to be looked into. It's a complete
absolute mess. It's a multi-dimensional
mess. uh India's far east has been
horribly mismanaged by India since 1947
since 1949 step step motherly treatment
has been given as a consequence of that
there have been so many insurgencies
which then foreign nations have taken
advantage of so this needs to be fixed
obviously it needs to be fixed so there
we are
um
MK says are the weapons that we sell to
other countries under the supervision
and control of Indian technicians
especially the uh the Philippines which
is a US facile well I don't have
information about this
uh the Philippines as we know has very
strong ties with the US we know that you
could be correct in saying the
Philippines is a US vasal no question
about it
and now there's even
stronger uh cooperation that's now
beginning to happen between the
Philippines and the US which is
something I discussed in the recent
episode of geost strategy that aired
48 or so hours ago. Uh so Philippines
obviously is a US facile and uh we have
sold if I'm not mistaken bramos missiles
the Philippines.
Now if you sell the if India sells the
bramos missile system to any country
country X country Y country Zed whatever
it will only happen if Russia approves
it because this is a jointly
co-developed co-produced missile system.
So both nations get a veto. If Russia
wants to sell it to country X then it
has to take India's permission. If India
wants to sell it to country X we have to
take Russia's permission. It can only
happen if both countries agree.
Now I expect that the missile system
that we sell to foreign countries will
be what we call an export version. It
will not be the full version that's used
by the Indian armed forces. It will be a
slightly watered down version and uh I'm
sure we we will have taken sufficient
care to ensure that no critical
technology falls into the hands of let's
say the master of the vasal right. uh
but whether we have uh Indian
technicians there or not I think only
the government of India will know about
it. It's not something that will be
disclosed to the rest of the world
including to Indian citizens. So I don't
know about that but I'm sure we have
taken sufficient precautions to ensure
that our critical technologies don't
fall into the hands of nations that may
not be very favorably inclined towards
us.
Saita Reddi says, "How could melting
Arctic sea routes reconfigure
Indo-Pacific maritime trade?
The Arctic region." Let's go and take a
look at the Arctic region on the map.
Okay. So, here we have the map of the
world. Now, you're talking about first
let's discuss the Indo-Pacific maritime
trade. So, the Indo-Pacific maritime
trade, there's no trade happening in the
Pacific. The nations that exist in the
Pacific are very very tiny nations.
These are the South Pacific nations like
Samoa, French Polynesia, the Cook
Islands, the Pitkan Islands which is
micros which is a micro nation
essentially. Very interesting history of
course but I'll not go into that. Uh
then we have Samoa, we have Fiji, we
have Tonga the capital of Tonga is it's
Nuku alfa. Where is Nuku alfa? Here we
have it. Nuku alfa the capital of Tonga.
Yeah GK question and so on. So these are
tiny nations. So the trade with those
nations doesn't really matter. Then we
have Hawaii which is a US uh which is a
US occupied region. Uh but see the trade
that happens between various nations. It
passes through various choke points as
we know. One is the straight of Bab
al-Mandde which is over here right the
other one is uh the so canal that's
another choke point. Then you have
energy choke point which is the straight
of hormos over here. the straight of
Orurum. Then we have this straight of
Malaa which is another choke point choke
point and so on and there's some more
which we can dis which so most of the
trade it passes through these choke
points Mala Sis Bab al-Mandde the energy
trade it has a choke point is as in u
the straight of Hormuz and because of
the recent problems in the Gulf of Aen
that's why a lot of the trade has been
routed across all the way down south
through the cape of why the cape of good
hope and so on. So the trade the trade
routes they essentially are between
large nations like India and China and
the western nations like the EU nations
and so on and also the United States. So
that trade could possibly go via the
Pacific.
Now just because the Arctic uh sea route
could open up doesn't mean that we need
to start using that and start bypassing
this region because most of the nations
over here the major nations they're far
from the Arctic and uh and they don't
really need I mean it doesn't really
make sense to go all the way north and
then you know transport goods via the
Arctic region. it will be significantly
more costly to do that. The reason why
the Arctic region is important is
because it will have significant uh
reserves of oil and natural gas. Okay.
uh and it is something that nations like
China and the northern European nations
and also North American nations that
could use that that would be interested
in that and obviously uh because of the
the reserves of oil and gas and other
other resources that will open up over
here that's why this region is uh it's
coming under increasing focus but uh in
my opinion it is not really because if
I'm I've shown you how far it
from the major nations. It's it's not
really an alternative
u sea route
which could replace the existing sea
routes. It's something that's important
because of the natural resources found
in the region. It is not really a viable
alternative alternative to reroute the
trading uh trading uh lanes for.
Okay.
Nandanda Takar says, "Did Mossad help
Adani from Hindenburg?" Listen, when you
talk about whether Mossad did this or
Mossad did that, do you think I am the
person to ask that? Do you think I work
for Mossad or I have connections in
Mossad?
Do you really think so?
Come on. Yeah, you better ask a Mossad
agent. I assure you I'm not. I have no
connections in Mossad. And uh
the the if Mossad did something you
think they will let me know about it.
Come on ask better better questions
please.
Aries Manticor says many fear monger
sanctions on India on Russian oil but it
is is it not an opportunity. Let them
eject us out of the global economy. It
could force us to evolve towards
self-reliance and fundamental changes.
Sure. Okay. uh it will leave India with
no option but to be self-reliant and so
on but it will co come at tremendous
cost and tremendous pain right and not
short-term cost and short-term pain
long-term I mean at least a couple of
decades worth and then our dear Indian
citizens will start whining and moaning
and crying that I have we now can no
longer get the benefit of this or that
or we no longer get our so-called our
our luxury goods we no longer get
iPhones we no longer get uh uh Android
phones. We no longer get this. We don't
we can no longer watch uh our favorite
uh Netflix for example. We no longer
have Amazon. I mean all kinds of
complaints will come in and of course we
will lose out on a lot of trading
opportunities GDP growth opportunities
which could
which could ensure that we don't reach
the uh 10 trillion dollar target GDP by
2020 whatever period time period
whatever target we target date we have
maybe 2030 right maybe we want to become
a 10 trillion economy by 2030 or 2035
we'll is that
so it's an opportunity of sorts. It's an
opportunity only if you're an utarch
only if you have u access to all the u
all the natural resources and everything
that that that are needed that are
necessary for a nation to grow. If you
don't have access to that then it's a
big problem. So for example we still
depend on other nations for our energy
oil and gas about 60 plus% of our energy
especially oil and gas comes from abroad
more than that I'm sure now if we have
sanctions and and the sanctions force
the Gulf nations to not trade with us
then what happens so we have to be
realistic that this is not merely an
opportunity. It's a huge problem. If
this happens, if they eject us out of
the global economy, we will no longer
have access to oil and gas.
Then what do we do? Go back to bulock
cuts. Go completely electric. Then what?
Then okay, then how do we generate the
electricity
by burning coal? But is coal enough? So
we have to be practical. We have to be
realistic and we have to
act in a manner that that ensures that
we don't really get sanctioned. Right?
Okay. MK says, "Why didn't the British
Empire apply the Thusid trap logic to
preemptively contain or attack Germany
before the World Wars?"
Um, well, now that's a lie.
Okay. So, it depends on the leadership.
It depends on a nation's leadership. If
a leadership, if your nation's
leadership isn't strong, if it is
historically illiterate, if it doesn't
realize, if it doesn't see the warning
signs, then well, even if you are a
powerful nation, you will be caught
napping,
right? So, I think that's what happened.
Uh, of course the UK did realize that
Germany before the second world war,
before the first world war, the UK did
realize that Germany is becoming a major
maritime power. It's developing a first
class
navy especially those Ubot the undersea
boats and so on and that's essentially
and they started taking steps uh to to
to militarize to militarize themselves
and all. It's it's pretty complicated.
The the First World War especially is an
extraordinarily complicated complicated
scenario. And what I can say in brief is
that if your leadership isn't good
enough and if if they don't see the
warning signs and if they see the
warning signs and don't realize what the
warning signs are telling you, then
yeah, then you'll be caught napping. And
that's kind of what happened. And even
when Hitler started remilitarizing
Germany, I mean Germany was not supposed
to militarize as per the agreement that
they had the treaty of Versailles and so
on. But Hitler started Hitler started
militarizing Germany and he and he uh
rescued the economy which was which was
in a terrible state and you could see
that Germany is militarizing. Germany is
becoming more and more aggressive and
assertive and uh dangerous. But what
would what did Chamberlain do? So he
went and tried to
negotiate and came back with a piece of
paper. Here we have it. Germany has
agreed to this or that. So it depends on
the quality of your leadership and if
your leadership isn't isn't good enough
then yeah you're going to mess up.
Geopolitical Dub says does Russia want
India to be a major arms exporter? I
don't think Russia will mind that. I
don't think Russia will mind that as
long as I mean see from Russia's
perspective they have their biggest
problem is the US obviously the entire
western block which is led by the US all
the other western nations are vasals of
the US the EU NATO nations and other
whatever the nations we have uh that's
the first big and the biggest problem
for Russia what's the second biggest
problem for Russia it's China
and Russia are natural adversaries they
are long-term adversaries right now they
are working together in what we call a
modus vive
uh because they have a bigger external
threat. But if that external threat goes
away, Russia and China will instantly
transform into enemies. Just like in the
second world war, the US and the USSR
were allies, weren't they? But the
moment the war ended, they became
enemies, adversaries.
That's the thing. So from Russia's
perspective, if the US is taken out of
the out of the equation, then China is
the biggest threat.
And what can counterbalance China in
Asia? It's India. So if India gets
stronger, if India becomes more
powerful, if India becomes a proper
major arms exporter, the Russians won't
mind it because India and Russia have
are not at loggerheads in anything. We
have no points of disagreement. We have
not no significant major disputes of any
kind.
Right. And if India becomes a major arm
exporter, Russia won't mind importing
arm from us either. So Russia will be
okay with it. They will not mind.
All right.
Tarun says, "If all Middle Eastern
countries were to unite like they did
under the Abbasad Khalifhat, would such
a union be as powerful and dominant
today as it was in Abbasid times? What
would be the major geopolitical
consequences?"
The Abbasid caliphate. The Abbasid
caliphate. We had the Umayyad, we had
the Rashidun, Abbasid. Let's just
quickly look at the time period of the
Abbasid Caliphate. Uh,
one second. Let me see.
Omayad Rashidun Abbasid. Abasid is just
before the first invasions of India,
right?
Abasid caliphate.
Yeah, there we have it. one u and it was
brought to the brought to an end by by
hleu Khan's capture and and destruction
of of Baghdad. Kleu Khan was uh a
descendant probably a grandson of great
probably grandson of Shir Chingghis
Khan. Uh yeah so it replaced the Umyad
caliphate in 750 CE and it was the
caliphate under which the first raids on
India on Sind happened. So look and and
if you look at this, yeah, it was a
pretty big uh unified block. Do we have
a better larger map? Yeah, here we have
it. So they controlled much of North
Africa, the entirety of uh
the entirety of the Arabian Peninsula,
mo mostly most of the Arabian Peninsula.
They had also conquered Persia sadly and
they were infringing on the borders of
India. They had already absorbed Sind
and so on. This was the Abbasad Khalif
at its greatest ex greatest extent more
or less.
So the question we have to ask ourselves
my friends is what made the Abbasid
Khalifhat so powerful? How was it able
to expand so much and conquer so much
territory
just because you had all these regions
unified under it? Was that why it was
powerful or were these regions unified
under it because it was so powerful? So
why did the Arabs become this dominant
force? First of all, it was Islam that
that unified them and it gave them this
this uh this militaristic ideology that
everything needs to be conquered,
everything needs to be destroyed, right?
Um the world is there, it exists for you
to conquer it and your purpose is to
convert the entire world to Islam. That
sort of thing. So that gave them this
militaristic zeal and they
they they they were a desert people.
They were used to hardship and they were
used to a regimented disciplined
militaristic life and when that is
combined with this religious zeal and
good tactics and strategies then you
know you can do wonders militarily. So
that's how they were able to do that and
at the time Persia was kind of weak and
the North African region was also you
know not unified under any any single
you know empire or whatever and then
Egypt was was also weak and that's why
they were able to conquer so much of the
world and they were able to make raids
into India as well the western parts of
India
so they were successful because and of
course they had good technologies and
all that as well uh techn
technologically they were pretty good
for for for that time probably some of
the best technology they of of the time
they they were employing those so that's
why they became so powerful and that's
why they were able to conquer so much of
the world now but today if the Middle
Eastern countries were to unite
somehow okay just like under the Abbasad
Khalifhat would that union be as so at
that time the Abbasad Khalifhat was
probably the most powerful um
geopolitical entity in the
possibly right
now if these Middle Eastern countries
were to come together unite under a
single let's say emperor Khalif again
today will they suddenly become as you
know the most dominant geopolitical
force in the world they won't
they won't
China will still be more powerful than
them Russia will be more powerful than
them none of the Middle Eastern
countries, Islamic countries possesses
the nuclear bomb,
right? And Pakistan won't become part of
this because the Americans won't allow
that to happen. So you have a big block
of nations that have combined together
to create a new caliphate, but they
don't have the military might.
They don't have the best technology.
Uh they may have some of them may have
F-16s or whatn not but the Americans can
kill those with the kill switch and then
the F-16s become museum pieces. They
won't take off or even if they take off
they won't lock onto targets the
Americans don't want them to lock lock
on to so militarily they're toothless.
They have some manpower but in today's
world the manpower doesn't matter. It's
technology that matters and they don't
have the nuclear bomb. So what do they
do? Even with a large portion of the
world unified under a caliphate, it will
not be a powerful force. There will be
no major geopolitical con consequences.
Yeah, they could kind of control much of
the world's oil
and so on. So that could give them some
leverage as a bargaining chip, but not
to that extent because the US is
completely self-sufficient when it comes
to oil and gas. So is Russia. Uh it
would give them some leverage over India
and China.
So that would be the it would be more of
u energy sort of leverage and a little
bit of geoeconomic leverage but not not
really any military leverage and that
too not over the US but over India and
China and maybe some EU nations. So
overall it will not make much of a much
of a difference. It will be nowhere as
powerful as the Abbasid caliphate was
but an interesting thought experiment
for sure.
Aries Manticor says, "Could a
dollarbacked cryptocurrency create a
dark economy?"
A dollarbacked cryptocurrency,
could it create a dark economy? It's a
parallel economy. It's not a dark
economy. Uh so we have cryptocurrencies
that exist in the world today. We have
Bitcoin, we have Ethereum, we have all
kinds of other various other currencies
of various kinds. Um, and you can use
those currencies to trade with people
who accept those currencies. And by
doing that, you can bypass
uh the the the
US dollar-based
financial system. You can bypass it for
sure. So that's a parallel economy
essentially. It's not a dark economy
and it's pretty secure actually if you
know what you're doing. But if you have
a dollarbacked cryptocurrency, then it
becomes nothing but an extension of the
US dollar's hedgemony, right? Because
see, right now the US dollar is it could
become worthless if all it takes is for
the nations to stop trading in the US
dollar and then the US dollar becomes
worthless because it is not backed up by
anything tangible. It's not backed up by
gold like it used to be until the until
the early '7s. Until the early '7s, the
US had committed that it will keep gold
reserves equal to the amount of dollar
bills in circulation. So if one dollar
bill was equivalent to X amount of gold,
X grams of gold, then and if you have X
so much dollars in circulation, then the
US was required by law to maintain that
much gold, physical gold in their
coffers. But after after Nixon came to
power, he ended that and the US dollar
became a free flowing free free floating
currency. Not backed up by anything. It
was backed up by petroleum for a while.
It was called the petro dollar. Today
it's backed up by nothing. It's backed
up by the US military might and nothing
else. Uh so if the Americans create a
dollarbacked cryptocurrency, then once
again that cryptocurrency is backed up
by the US military might and all it
takes is for people to just ignore it
and not not trade in in it to to make it
worthless. So it won't create a dark
economy. It may at most at best create a
parallel economy which will be tied to
the actual economy and that defeats the
purpose of cryptocurrency.
So yeah, it won't really make sense for
people who want to trade in
cryptocurrency cryptocurrencies to use
that dollar backed cryptocurrency
because then you are defeating the
purpose of creating crypto
cryptocurrencies in the first place.
Dr. Rita Debnat says, "Why is the US
interested in entering the dairy
business in India? Do they really think
they can provide our population with
milk daily? What's the foul play here?"
Um,
the US wants to enter every aspect of
the Indian economy because uh they want
to turn India into a giant market. First
of all, a dumping ground for their
products so that they can extract value
out of India.
And when it comes to dairy and
agriculture,
uh their products are genetically
modified,
their cows have been genetically
modified, their crops have been
genetically modified. These are
laboratory laboratory experiments that
they're playing. And you can see the
consequences of that in the average
health of the average person in the US.
Everybody is unhealthy.
All the meat they eat is is messed up.
All the dairy they drink is messed up.
The the all their food products are are
toxic, filled with chemicals and god
knows what. And these genetic
experiments,
they could end up creating all kinds of
downstream effects which would be
extremely dangerous uh for people.
So they want to get that into India
and that is something that is
that that the government of India is
obviously resisting because it makes
sense to resist that we don't want our
population to fall prey to all this.
So the reason they want to do this is
they want to
they they they want to essentially well
there's no better way of saying it. They
want to poison us. Yeah. The way they
have poisoned their people, they want to
bring that into India. And obviously
there could be some um patented product
products that they will push into India.
So on the one hand they extract money
out of India by selling their
substandard and in poisoned stuff and
secondly they get to poison the people
of India and uh yeah create long-term
genetic problems in India. So one of the
things the British did in India okay was
by by imposing two and a half centuries
of famine on the Indian population they
changed the food habits of Indians. The
Indian diet became extremely heavily
carbohydrate dependent. If you see the
Indian diet today it's all
carbohydrates. There's hardly any
protein.
And because of this, Indians are
extremely
are are way more susceptible to diabetes
than other other populations in the
world because of the two and a half
centuries of starvation that the British
imposed on India. So that kind of
changed the genetics of India. Now the
Americans want to do it in in a
different way by specifically targeting
you know certain genetics using
genetically modified dairy products and
and and agricultural products. So it's
it's something that India should resist.
We should not agree to import this
garbage and that seems to be the bone of
contention right now when it comes to
the trade deal trade talks with India
and between India and the US. The trade
talks have stalled from what I hear.
They're not progressing because the
Americans are insisting that India
should accept their agricultural exports
and we are saying we will not do that.
So that's the that's the deal.
Okay. Shivan Bakshi says
interesting UK, France are going down
the hill with immigration. There's
nothing they can do but the US can kick
illegals with a whim. Pardon my French.
You haven't used any French. So,
okay.
So, the US can kick illegals out
anytime. Yeah. Trump wants to kick all
the illegals out. That's what he has
kept on saying, but how many have they
actually
deported? Trump came to power in January
this year. How many illegal immigrants
of the Americans kicked out thus far?
There has been some some action possibly
on that, but I'm not sure. They have
deported like tens of thousands or
hundreds of thousands thus far. It is
believed that during the Biden Biden
administration's four years in power,
several million undocumented illegal
immigrants were allowed to were brought
into the US by the Biden administration
mainly mainly through the southern
border with Mexico. How many of these
have been deported? I'm not sure. A lot
have been. But if Trump wants, I'm sure
he can get everyone deported.
But the UK and France aren't allowed to
do that. The EU nations aren't allowed
to do that. Um there's nothing they can
do. So that's how it goes. See, this is
what you could call demographic
re-engineering of Europe that is being
done. And obviously uh the root cause of
all of that is the US. The US is the
overlord of Europe. The major power in
Western Europe is the US. It's not
Germany. It's not France. It's not the
UK. It is the US. it's the US and
whatever is being done to Europe is
being done at the behest of the US. So
yeah, they are re-engineering the
demographics of Europe and there's
nothing the European nations can do
about this. And this is all being done
via Brussels which is the headquarters
of the EU. And uh if you are a member of
the EU then you are not sovereign
because the policies that will apply to
your nation and it that will apply to
your population your public will be
decided outside of your country. They'll
be decided in Brussels.
So you are you don't have territorial
sovereignty you don't have legislative
sovereignty either.
Um and that's how you can mess up an
entire nation's demographic. So that's
what's being done.
Backbenture academy lover says how
geopolitically relevant is astrology
vast etc. I have absolutely no idea.
Sorry.
Arun says why are Iranian Shia Muslims
who migrated to India in huge numbers
equal to Pakistan's Pakistanis and
Afghans not viewed as a concern despite
strong religious cultural and
ideological ties to Iran a key
geopolitical prayer player look I don't
talk about about religious matters and
all I I'm not sure about this this is
something I'm not aware of okay um
yeah this is something that I don't look
into religious aspects and Hindu Muslim
stuff and Shia versus Sunni and the
difference between Shia people and Sunni
people and all that. I I am not aware of
this. Sorry, I won't be able to answer
this question because I'm I'm not aware
of this. Sorry.
Above says, "What power is behind mass
immigration in Europe?" The United
States.
As simple as that.
Godliness says reports mention French
naval data including their nuclear
submarine details have been leaked. Of
course to be leaked they have to be
hacked. Right. There are reports
mentioning US and Israeli links to this
leak. Are Indians Corpin class submarine
details also at risk is the question. So
yes uh today one woke up when one heard
to the news that u French naval data has
been leaked
including details about the nuclear
submarines.
Um and there have been reports I don't
know I've not seen the reports but yeah
I mean I'm hearing chatter I'm hearing
whispers that maybe the US and the
Israelis are behind this. Do we know
who's behind this? We don't know. But
could the US and Israel be behind this?
Possibly. Well, possibly. It's always a
possibility. Maybe Russia is behind it.
Maybe China is behind it. Maybe the US
may be behind. Maybe the Israelis may be
behind it. But logically, who could it
be is the question logically? Let's
think about this logically. What
happened recently between France and
Israel? Well, recently Mu Mak the French
president, he officially recognized the
state of Palestine.
He recognized Palestine as a nation. Is
Palestine a nation? Is it? It's not a
nation. Where is the nation of
Palestine? Where does it exist? Is it
Gaza? That little little square piece of
land, is that the nation of Palestine?
Is the West Bank of the River Jordan, is
that what is Palestine? Has something
called Palestine existed historically?
Has there ever been a kingdom or an
empire or a nation of called Palestine?
Where does this name Palestine come
from? It comes from the Philistine
people who existed in in the region of
Israel about 2 and a half thousand years
ago. What does that have to do with the
Arabs who claim to be Palestinians? I so
this so the French have gone ahead and
taken this step. They have recognized
the state of Palestine and obviously
Israel is super upset about that. I I
would not blame them for that. Right
now, does this concern me? It doesn't
concern me. It's something that's
between the two nations, France and
Israel. Okay? So, that's their problem.
That's their bilateral problem, let's
say, from my perspective. And it doesn't
have anything to do with us. Now if
France takes this kind of step which is
you could say a hostile and aggressive
step towards Israel
then should Israel just sit back and
take it
given Israel's history do you think they
will not retaliate in some way?
Historically Israel has retaliated
whenever somebody has taken hostile
steps against them. So maybe
maybe possibly perhaps Israel could
potentially be behind this, but it's
pure speculation. There is no evidence
of that, right? Uh so yeah, possibly
possibly Israel could perhaps
hypothetically be behind this. I'm not
saying it is. I'm not saying it isn't.
I'm saying there's a possibility. Now
the Indian scorpion class submarine. So
uh we have a bunch of scorpion class
submarines that we operate. These are a
French design. These were built I think
yeah there are definitely at least a few
of them were built in India. Um
and uh the design is a French design uh
the scorpion class. So is
are are submarines also at le risk
because of the data that was leaked out?
I am not sure but possibly they could
there could be some sensitive data that
may have leaked out. Um if if if data
corresponding to scorpion class
submarines as a as a class is leaked out
that will definitely apply to Indian
scorpion class submarines as well even
if they have been modified in some way
and to be and tailored specifically for
for India but some of the specific
specifications will remain the same. So
I think there's a possibility
that some data pertinent to Indian
scorpion class submarines may also have
been leaked out as part of this wider
leak of French naval data. So the Indian
Navy, the Indian government need to look
into it very very very very seriously
and take whatever action needs to be
taken ASAP as soon as possible. Right.
Okay. Draj Kamat says Israel is
currently attacking Syria apparently
with the Drews genocide unlike India
with respect to Bangladesh Hindus. Yeah,
we aren't doing a thing about the
genocide of Bangladesh Hindus in
Bangladesh. Yeah,
this is despite them being geopolitical
allies
apparently. What are my thoughts? Okay,
let's take a look at the map so that we
can uh orient and locate orient
ourselves and locate the region we are
talking about.
So if you look here, you will see that
Israel and Syria are neighboring
countries. Okay, here we have Israel
and we have Jordan.
And if you go to the northern part of of
Israel, you will see that it's it's got
a border with Syria. The border
obviously is all dashed up and all that.
And Israel has been somewhat expanding
its border
eastwards to a to some extent possibly.
Okay. And uh for the longest time we had
the Assad regime in Syria, the the
government of Mr.
al-Assad
Bashar al-Assad and uh a few months ago
there was a coup regime regime change
operation successful regime operation
that happened and Mr. Bashar al-Assad
had to flee to Moscow and a terrorist
has come to power in Damascus. His name
is Al Julani or something
Alulani. His actual name is Al- Shara.
Uh yeah, I don't get these are all
foreign names so I'm I'm not good at
speaking these names. But yeah, let's
call him Mr. Alulani. He is a former
wanted terrorist. I think a $10 million
bounty on his head. But now he's an ally
of the West. And uh let's let's see uh
what Mr. Trump has done recently.
Okay.
So Trump golani
al-Sh
posing with a terrorist
uh Trump al-Shar
shah
so we have Mr. Donald Trump, the
president of the US, posing with
a person who was until recently regarded
as a terrorist by the United States.
There we have it.
So now, so that means that uh this
terror, this former terrorist is now a
western ally, a US ally, right? And if
he's an ally of the US, well, it
technically makes him an ally of Israel
because the US is Israel's number one
ally. And that that means that any
American ally will automatically be
regard should be regarded as as an
Israeli ally.
So you have Golani who is in power in
Damascus
and uh he's running the country and
Israel bombed Damascus just a few days
ago and Israel is is conducting military
operations in Syria and the
justification being given is that the
the al-Shani
regime is conducting a genocide of the
Drews people.
So what's going on is the question. What
exactly is going on? If this guy is your
ally, if you have an allied government
there, then let them do what they want.
Why are you why are you attacking them?
So you know, and who are these Drews
people? The Drews people are an Arabic
people who practice an Abrahamic
religion called the Drews religion.
And it's not Islam. It's a different
religion. And uh if you are a Syri
a terrorist like Alara, you will regard
the Drews people as non-Muslims and I
suppose they're supposed to be killed
apparently according to their ideology.
I don't know. I don't get it. But that's
how it works for them. So there's a
genocide possibly going on of the Drews
people. They are being attacked and
they're being killed and all that and
Israel possibly is taking action because
of that. Is is that really why Israel is
attacking Syria or does Israel have some
other geopolitical agenda? So, some
people allege, some people claim that
Israel wants to expand its territory and
create a greater Israel. That's what
some people claim. Is it true? Well, I
don't know about that. Some people make
that allegation. And some people put out
a map of greater Israel, which kind of
includes large areas of Syria. Is that
the reason why Israel is doing this? I
don't know. We'll have to wait and
watch. Okay. Uh so the official reason
possibly is that this is being done to
stop the genocide of the Drews people
and some people are alleging that Israel
wants to expand its territory. We'll
have to wait and watch and see what's
really happening.
Koshel Panchchal. Thank you very much
sir. Thank you.
Uh Aintan says what are websites that
one should use to research geopolitics
in history as many of the books are
agendadriven. So first of all um
okay we'll talk about geopolitics here.
History that's a whole different story.
We are not discussing history today.
Let's talk about geopolitics.
What websites can you use to research
geopolitics
and what books can you read to research?
Okay books. You're not asking about
books. First of all there are no books
about geopolitics. Have you seen a
textbook of geopolitics anywhere in the
world?
there there's no textbook of
geopolitics.
Are there any courses in universities
that teach you geopolitics?
I don't think so.
You generally are taught strategy,
military history, military tactics and
strategy. You taught history, but you I
have never seen any any any course in
geopolitics.
So there aren't really any books on
geopolitics. If you want to read books
on geopolitics, you have to read books
that are related to military strategy,
books that are related to diplomacy, the
books that are related to uh foreign
policy. And using all this together, you
kind of form an idea of what geopolitics
is kind of like. But the best way to
study geopolitics is to study a lot of
history. And then you kind of start
seeing the patterns and the cyclical
nature of things. Now, what websites can
you use to research geopolitics? I
suppose you just read the news. read the
news and form try and form patterns and
connections because there's no
geopolitics website. Is there a website
called geopolitics.com or whatever?
There are some think tanks, right? Um
there are some think tanks that do exist
that do discuss foreign policy matters.
uh and then then there are some
publications like what foreign
policy.com or something
and uh so as far as India is concerned I
don't know of any any major
think tank or publication that deals
with uh foreign policy issues and
geopolitical issues but from the US
there are many there's the Atlantic
which is which used to be great in the
past not so great these days there's the
national interest that talks about the
American national interest and
geopolitics from that perspective
There is foreign policy I believe that
all of that is from the American
perspective. There's ASPI
I forget it's an Australian thing that's
a think tank that put puts forth policy
I mean policy recommendations and uh
deep dive analysis of various
geopolitical things you know all there
is that
and what else yeah so you have to read
all of these all of this and and keep
keep track of what these people are
recommending of obviously there's rand
corporation which is uh which has now
turned into a US propaganda outlet kind
of. It used to be highly respectable in
the past, but it has a dodgy history
which I'll not go into right now. So
yeah, that's what you do. I suppose
that's what you do.
Baratia says Russia may forment problems
for us internally or geopolitically more
than US or China if we were to develop
undemand crude reserves into a full OMG
ecosystem as they will lose significant
revenue. No,
no, no. They won't. They won't. See,
first of all, if we do, if we do um
let's say discover
significant reserves of of oil of crude
oil in the Andermans.
First of all, any such discovery hasn't
been announced. We are drilling in the
Andermans and it's possible that we may
find something. I've been saying this
for a long time. If we start drilling
everywhere, we'll find more oil and gas
than than in the Persian Gulf and
Arabian Peninsula region. I'm sure we
will. So, I think it's a matter of time
before we find some some major crude oil
discovery. If that happens, we become
energy self-sufficient in energy. We
potentially may become an exporter of
energy. But to reach that state of
becoming self-sufficient and then
becoming an exporter will take at least
10 years, 5 10 years at least because
you have to first discover the oil
reserves. Then you have to go and uh you
know create those those oil rigs on top
of that which can be used to extract the
oil. Then then you have to develop the
refineries which can refine all of that
crude oil into finished products. All of
that process all of the setting up of
the infrastructure all all of that will
take 5 10 years minimum right and so it
won't happen overnight that today India
is purchasing tremendous amounts of
Russian Russian crude and tomorrow
morning we stop everything won't happen
like that it'll be a slow gradual
process and if India becomes
self-sufficient in energy it's great for
India it's also great for Russia yeah
sure they will lose out on some revenue
but it's not India's fault and secondly
it'll make India much stronger nation
compared to China because China doesn't
have self-sufficiency in terms of energy
but if India becomes self-sufficient in
terms of energy it gives India
significant energy advantage and overall
geopolitical advantage over China which
is great for Russia so Russia won't mind
it they won't forment any problems for
us internally or geopolitically they
have never done that so I I don't
foresee that this to be a problem at all
Rahul Lakshmanan says is China likely to
view us India India as a rival against
the west or a bulv war against the west
in the near to midterm China will always
see India as a rival. Okay. Even when
there is maybe a kaposhimo maybe the
tant maybe a diplomatic
th whatever you want to call it between
India and China will always regard India
as a rival. China may try and use India
use India as a bulv war to some extent
against the west. Perhaps they may try
to do use it use us in that manner but
note the word use.
They will try to use us against
somebody. They'll never try to help us.
So, and I'm not sure if if it's even a
good idea for us to,
you know, allow China to export stuff to
us in large large quantities because
they have this uh over capacity in
manufacturing and they need to export
their stuff somewhere. Now, it's not no
longer possible to export their their
Fedish products to the west anymore
because of the trade war, the tariff war
that's going on. So, they would like to
do that to India. But if they start
dumping their products into India, it
will kill Indian manufacturing.
So I don't think it's a good idea. I
don't think it's a good idea for us to
go down that road. Then we will remain
dependent on some foreign country or the
other. For us, it's imperative to become
completely self-sufficient in terms of
manufacturing, in terms in in in when it
comes to technology.
We cannot remain dependent on other
countries. Uh so China will always
regard India as a rival and China will
have to be regarded as a rival by us
always no matter what is currently going
on. Currently they have been friendly to
us. So what we are natural adversaries
and natural rivals as long as China
occupies Tibet. The moment China
withdraws from Tibet we can be friends
again.
But as long as they are in occupation of
Tibet India and China are natural
rivals. All right.
IC MBS says subs or aircraft carriers.
What's more important? Subs. Always
subs.
Aircraft carriers are good to have. When
you are a $30 trillion economy, when you
are the most powerful nation in the
world and nobody dares to
dares to try and hit you, that's when
you can use aircraft carriers
to bully others to display force to to
as a show of force as for the purpose of
power projection. But you will see that
aircraft carriers will not be used even
by the US in contested waters.
They'll stay away from contested waters.
Have you seen aircraft carriers being
deployed near Yemen by the Americans?
They've stayed away from Yemen.
Okay. Aircraft carriers cannot be used
in contested waters, in contested
airspace.
Dangerous. Super dangerous. Submarines.
You can sneak a submarine into into the
enemy's harbor if you want. The
submarine is the most dangerous asset a
navy can have. Aircraft carriers are
good to have. It's prestigious and you
can use that to bully the weak. But you
can't use them in contested waters or
contested airspace. Always submarines.
And I hope the Indian Navy
understands this.
Karthik says
who will win the Muslim caucases
like Dagistan, Chachchna, Ingushyak
etc. Turkey, Iran, Russia in terms of
geopolitical dominance.
Look when it comes to Dagistan,
Cheschna, Ingusetya, all of that it all
belongs to Russia.
You think Turkey and Iran are in a
position to win that from Russia?
Absolutely not.
Right. Right. Let's go to the map. Let
me show you. Okay. It's it's not a bad
question actually. Let's take a look at
because because most people don't know
about what is Inguushetya, what is
Chichchna, what is Dagistan.
So we're talking about the Caucasus
region over here. See you see this place
Makkala
that is Dagistan. It's the largest city
possibly the capital of the region of
Dagistan. When it comes to Cheschna, the
capital is Grozni.
This here, that's Cheschna. These are
Muslim regions. Okay? These people were
converted to Islam in the past few
centuries. Uh which one was converted
more recently, Chachchna or Dagasan? I
don't remember. Ingushetya. Let's look
for Ingushya.
Ingushetya
once again is this little region over
here. Pretty small region.
And so that's what we're talking about.
These are the the so-called small
republics of Cheschna, Dagistan,
uh, Ingosetia and so on. And all of this
belongs to Russia.
Turkey is in no position to take this
from Russia. Neither is Iran.
And that, I suppose, is the answer.
That's it. Right. So it it belongs to
Russia and it's it's not contested at
all in any any any manner.
Right. Okay. What else do we have? We
have here this here. Aishwari Nagar
says, "Can India regain its power status
given the fact that we are surrounded by
hostile/failed
nations?" By the way, the UK lost that
that that status just because its
enemies were nearby.
The UK lost its status because its
Yeah. Which enemies were nearby?
The UK lost its uh empire.
Yeah, it did. The UK was the dominant
superpower of the world until the 1930s
or so, maybe 1910, 1920s.
But it's started its power started
waning.
Now it lost its imperial status to
somebody else. Who was that? It was the
US. Is the US near the UK? The US is far
far from the UK.
What other nations were nearby? Yeah, we
had the Second World War. Germany and
historically France was the enemy of was
for a thousand years an enemy of the UK.
But that has nothing to do with the UK
losing its dominant status. It has
nothing to do with that.
So I'm not sure what the parallels are
over here. Uh can India regain its power
status? Which status are you talking
about? The past 1,000 years roughly
various parts of India were under
foreign occupation.
Right?
Uh of course the whole of India wasn't
under foreign occupation a thousand
years ago but it started with the fall
of Gandhar.
So that's where the first encroachment
happened and then slowly the Turks made
inroads into India and and you know what
happened. So we started losing our
territories more than a thousand years
ago and our power was declining ever
since.
So what power status are you talking
about? Are you talking about the the
Morian times when Ashok was in power?
Emperor Ashok, one of our greatest
emperors. Are you talking about the
times of Kaneshka?
Are you talking about the Chola times?
Are you talking about the Marata times?
I'm I'm not sure what. We are a
reasonably powerful nation. But
obviously if you're talking about power
status,
are you talking about India becoming the
most powerful country in the world?
We are a reasonable power reasonably
powerful nation. But we are not anywhere
close to being the most powerful nation.
Can we become the most powerful nation
one day? It's possible. Anything is
possible.
But how do we do it is the question. You
become powerful through technology.
Today we are trying to replicate
technology other nations have developed
20, 30, 40 years ago,
right? Jet engines for example.
What's what else? Nuclear reactors,
fighter planes. What other nations did
20, 30, 40 years ago, we are trying to
do it today. We're trying to play
catchup.
We're trying to develop LLMs, AI that
other nations have done. Now the AI time
time frames are significantly
significantly compressed. So the way to
become the most powerful nation is by
developing the best technology in the
world. Today the differentiator
when it comes to power is technology.
Imagine tomorrow India develops
the technology. Let's say let me give
you a completely fictional hypothetical
science fiction example. Let's say India
develops anti-gravity technology
tomorrow.
That way with that technology we can
lift any amount of matter into space in
a matter of minutes thousand tons to
space into into earth orbit. Sure let's
do it. That would give India complete
domination of the space domain
which would be a gamecher. It would
transform India into superpower
overnight.
Right? Technology is the differentiator.
That's what we need to do. But for that
we need to reform our education system
so that the Indian genius can can be
unleashed.
Right? So a lot of reforms will have to
be done and if we do that then yeah we
can certainly become the most powerful
nation in the world.
[Applause]
Napoleon Singh Shikhawad says, "Was
Nasir Nosher Gawadia framed?
Was China and the US involved in the guy
who developed stealth technology? Is
that who you're referring to?" Let me
quickly Google him.
Pretty obscure name, but there was a guy
who developed stealth technology for the
US. Noshir go.
Exactly. This is the guy who was
instrumental in developing stealth
technology for the United States. He was
born in Mumbai. He was Indian. He
migrated to the US in 1963.
And he was one of the principal
designers of the B2 Spirit stealth
bomber.
He conceived and conceptually designed
the B2 bomber's entire propulsion
system. This guy. Okay.
and he was arrested for being a spy in
2005 and was convicted. I suppose he is
in prison right now. He is currently
incarcerated in some some whatever
prison in the US 32 years in prison.
So was he framed? I have no idea. I
don't know. He was interviewed twice,
blah blah blah, etc., etc., etc. Trial
and so on.
Uh so so allegedly he transferred some
some technology in he sold classified
information to China and to individuals
in Germany, Israel in Switzerland. Is it
true? Is it not true? Was he framed? I
don't know. But yes, I I remember that.
Yeah. So the name the moment you said
noir Gowardia, I was like yeah, I think
that's the case you're talking about.
the guy who developed the B2 stealth
bomber, the propulsion system, stealth
technology, because that is part of the
stealth characteristics.
So, I don't know. I don't know if the
China if if he was framed or not. Maybe
he was. I don't know.
Anonymous scientist says, "We know a lot
about the deep state in the US and
China. Which other nations have a strong
deep state? How much power do they
wield?" Do we know that the Chinese have
a deep state? When you talk about deep
state, the only nation you're talking
about is the US. You're not referring to
China. When you say deep state, what
deep state does the ch does do the
Chinese have? They have the Chinese
Communist Party. We know where the power
lies. It lies in the Chinese Communist
Party's polit bureau and in the emperor,
the the Mr. Xinping and whoever will
eventually replace Mr. Xinping. That's
where the power lies. There's nothing.
There's no hidden power in China. As far
as we know, nobody refers to some hidden
power center in China. When you talk
about the deep state, you're only
referring to the US. You're not talking
about the the Chinese or any other
European country or anything else.
Um, and listen, when you ask me about
what how much power does any other deep
state yield, you asking me as if I am
aware of, okay, this is the deep state.
These are the members and this is how
much power they have and how much money
they have. A deep state is supposed to
be something completely hidden. How will
I know about this?
How will I know about this? I I am very
honored that you think that I may know
about it, but I don't. Come on. I only
know what's accessible in the public
domain. And even if I were to know
possibly about something, do you think I
would be stupid enough to speak about
this in public?
If you know about it, you don't speak
about it. You do not. What is the first
rule of F club? You do not speak about
flight club.
Okay. Rashi Kudin says
France recognized Palestine but also
support Israel rights thoughts. Yeah.
I'm not sure what what the French are up
to, what Mu is attempting to perform.
What is it trying to do? It's it's
signaling. It's it's virtue signaling.
um by recognizing a f fictional country
that doesn't exist. What are you trying
to achieve? You're trying to signal
something. You're trying to send a
message to whoever. Some of it is virtue
signaling. Some of that may stem from an
antipathy possibly between the two lead
between the two leaders. I'm not sure
what it is. Um the France obviously also
supports Israel's right to exist of
course, right? and for Israel's right to
defend itself from terrorists
any any civilized nation has to support
that right uh so yes France
I'm not sure why they have taken the
step of recognizing Palestine and they
seem to they seem to have got immediate
blowback from somewhere with the leakage
of all that classified naval information
right my thoughts I I mean I'm not sure
what they are trying to achieve by doing
this what's the point it's a fictional
nation it doesn't exist
Darth V says, "Do you agree that the
that the US is the biggest sponsor of
terrorism?"
Look, I'll tell you what.
It is undeniable that the US
funded and financed
Pakistani terrorism against India for
several decades. No question about that.
Pakistan is the world's biggest state
sponsor of terror the biggest exporter
of terrorism the biggest creator and
exporter of terrorism that's Pakistan
and its primary patron was the US for
several decades even today the US is the
overlord of Pakistan so that's what I
will tell you
that's that is undeniable even the
Americans can't deny this that they
funded and financed Pakistani terrorism
for decades beyond that I'll
go into other matters.
Backbenture Academy lover says, "Please
tell your thoughts on Vasu." I don't
know, sir, anything about Vasu. I don't
know anything about astrology. I have
never read a single page about Vasu or
astrology, let alone a book. I have
absolutely zero knowledge about Vasu,
about astrology and whatever else may be
related to that. So, I am sorry. I am
not the right person to ask this
questions. I'm going to talk about
geopolitics today. Let us stick to
geopolitics. Thank you and sorry I can't
answer this question because I don't
have any knowledge. Okay.
Look, I am taking questions about
geopolitics today. I have said that very
clearly. That's what the audience is
here to watch.
I have announced one week ago that this
super chat episode is a geopolitics
episode. So all the viewers who are
watching this right now and who will
watch this after it is when it is after
it is live people will watch it later
also they will come because they will
see the title geopolitics but if I start
talking about vastu I start talking
about astrology I start talking about
satwanas and history then I am
I'll be disappointing my audience right
so please I have said this very clearly
I will not take questions that are not
related to geopolitics I've even put a
pinned comment but still you are doing
this. I'm happy to answer history
questions in other live streams but
please respect my dear friends the fact
that this is a geopolitics liveream
okay I will take this question in a
future live stream which will be open to
other topics I'll be happy to right now
I can't take this
okay current says I have visited Iran
it's false that Iran has that Islam has
faded from Iran Shiraas, Toberis and
Ishan were packed with devout Shia
during Muharam. I haven't seen a mass
such a massive crowd such massive crowds
before. Can Iran still be seen as a
lasting Shia geopolitical force?
Well, I haven't visited Iran. So, I
think you have be better firsthand
knowledge of Iran than me. Okay, I have
to give that to you. And you went to
Shirro's Torres is Fhon and you saw
large crowds crowds like you have never
seen before. Does that mean that the
entirety of Iran
is represented by what you saw in those
three four places?
doesn't mean that let's say
what's okay let's see okay let's let's
quickly look into this h let's do a
Google search
shir
shir population
2025 what's the population
uh 1.7 million
let's say you are you saw a crowd of
300,000 three lakh people. That's a
gigantic ginormous crowd. Maybe you show
a crowd of 500,000.
Half a million. I mean I I can't imagine
So even that is less than one/ird of the
population of what about to
population? It is 1.7 million. Let's say
you crowd of you saw a crowd of 300,000.
How? It's it's about 1 16th of the
population of Tabris. What's is Fahhan?
Is Fahan?
2.33
million. So these are enormous
populations each of these cities and you
saw pretty large crowds. Does it mean
that everybody in that city is just as
devout? Let's say I have a city of 1
million people and 200,000 of those or
let's say half a million of those are
devout Shia Muslims and when there is a
muharam whatever they will come out in
big in a big procession and maybe three
lakh come out that's that's a huge crowd
but still it means that half the city
may not be that devout right so I know
you experience something incredible but
it doesn't nec necessarily mean that
that the whole of Islam, the whole of
Iran is super Islamic and all that.
Okay? Please don't allow your personal
experiences to cloud your judgment.
I understand the fact that you have been
there. I haven't been there. So, you
have better firsthand knowledge. But
sometimes your firsthand knowledge will
cloud your perception
of what statistics may represent. So I I
am hearing anecdotal
evidence, okay, that Islam is possibly
fading from Iran, that maybe half of
Iran no long the half of the Iranian
population no longer uh actively
practices is Islam. That's what I hear
now. Even that is hearsay.
So even that may not be true, right? So
I think the the truth may lie somewhere
in between.
But uh so that's what I can say. So my
point is don't let your personal
experiences uh cloud your judgment.
Right. What do we have? What else do we
have? One second. Let me find the next
question.
Abhinab says, "Thoughts on US Golden
Dome? Will it enable the US to launch
nuclear strikes without worrying about
retaliatory nuclear strikes by China or
Russia?" No.
No matter how good your missile defense
system is, it is not foolproof. It is
not guaranteed to be 100% effective.
Okay.
The US Golden Dome. What is it like?
Let's once again let's let's Google it.
US Golden Dome.
Dome. Dome. It's a proposed missile
defense system. Uh layered defense
system. Defense system. Global
constellation of satellites. Sensors
space-based. Oh my god. They're going to
militarize space. Very good. Then don't
blame others. Then later detect and
destroy incoming missiles including B.
So it it reminds me of something that
was very very hyped up in the 1980s when
I was a little kid. There was Star Wars.
Reagan Star Wars.
One second.
Yeah. Reagan Star Wars
strategic defense initiative derisively
nicknamed the Star Wars program and I
remain the I remember these these um
yeah these graphics they had put out.
So I'm not I'm not saying that because
Star Wars did not work and all it means
that Golden Dome won't work but this is
a proposed missile defense system. I
don't know how long it'll take and no
matter how good your missile defense
system is, it is not guaranteed to take
to to it's not guaranteed to destroy all
incoming bogeies. All right. And it's
it's going to be a multi-layered defense
system. So some of the interception will
be done by space-based assets like
satellites. So they are militarizing
space. Then they can't blame other
countries for militarizing space in
return. So some of the interceptions may
be done in space by space- based assets.
Some of them may be done by groundbased
assets like you know missiles that you
launch from the ground. There may be
laser systems in there. So it's a it's a
multi-layered defense system which makes
sense but even then it's not necessary
that it it will intercept everything. So
it will definitely give the US
possibly much better defense against
incoming missiles than they have right
now but it will not guarantee
100% interception rate.
Um
and obviously when you def when you
design and and implement a multi-layered
defense system like this, your
adversaries will go hard at will will be
hard at work immediately to design
systems that will bypass that. It's
always a cat and mouse game. I'm
developing a better defense system. So
my adver advertisers will come to know
about that and they will start
developing better missile systems that
will bypass my defenses. Then I
understand what defense what missiles
they're developing. So I'll try and
augment my defense system and they will
come to hear about it. So they will
start augmenting their offensive systems
as well. So it's a cat and mouse game.
It doesn't guarantee anything for
anybody.
Okay. Ankita says there's an ongoing
mass killing and brutal slaughtering of
dus people uh who are minorities in
Syria and uh the west is comfortably
silent. Is this so is this the kind of
regime change the west was advocating
for so many years? What's my opinion?
Well,
that's what the west does.
This is the standard time-tested
timehonored modus operandi of the west.
Do you know what happened in Indonesia
in the 1950s?
H
let's let's Google this. I mean there's
there's a humanitarian disaster
happening right now in in in in uh in
East Africa. No one knows about this. No
one hears about this. But let's talk
about
Indonesia
regime change
Indonesia mid60s mid60s. So there was a
transition from Sukarno's old order to
Suharto's new o new new order.
Um
and it read it led to Suharto's rise to
power in Sukarno's removal,
authoritarian rule, suppression of
descent,
um transition to the new order
and what happened as a consequence of
this United States assistance to
Suhartha. Oh, very nice. That's very
good. Indonesian mass killings
of
foreign
foreign involvement. Where is that? CIA
activities. Very nice. Very nice.
Indonesian mass killings of 1965-66.
How many died?
About between 500,000 to 1 million.
Okay. Official figures.
You have no idea the of the horrors that
were unleashed in his in in Indonesia.
as a consequence of this US mediated
regime change stage operation.
Horrific. And now today they make movies
about this in the US. What was it
called? The movie. I would not recommend
anybody to watch that movie by the way.
And it's a good thing I don't remember
the name right now.
So when the US does a regime change
operation, it's natural for all kinds of
barbaric things to happen. Absolutely
natural. You have to understand it's
it's it's a given.
I mean when there was the the liberation
of Libya from Muhammad Gaddafi, Muhammad
Gaddafi was uh deposed and and brutally
murdered, right, by the Americans? Then
what happened? Was there a transition to
democracy and freedom and human rights
in Libya? No. No. No. No. No. No. No.
No. No. No. No. No. No. No. Libya became
an open slave market.
What's the condition of Libya today?
It's a hell hole. Who did that? The
United States.
When the US liberated uh Iraq
from Shri Saddam Hussein, did what
happened? Did you get freedom and human
rights and democracy in in Iraq? Yeah.
Today, apparently have elections in
Iraq. Oh, great. What what what else
happened? Iraq became a hell hole.
So now you have
so now you have Syria they have been
trying to depose Bashar al-Assad since
2009 2010 thereabouts right that's when
the whole so-called civil war started
when the Americans started employing
first al-Qaeda as an American proxy and
then ISIS emerged out of nowhere
again another US proxy and so on so now
that Al Gulani or Al Shara whatever his
name is has taken over former a
terrorist. Well, now what do you expect?
He's going to carry out whatever he
wants to carry out. So, yeah, the Drews
people are being first it was the
Yazidis. So, when ISIS was slaughtering,
enslaving, and whatever else they were
doing to the Yazidis. Yeah. I mean,
unspeakable atrocities and horrors, what
was the US doing? Don't they believe in
human rights and freedom and democracy?
What did they do about the poor Yazidi
people? I hear I I I read somewhere
yesterday or day before yesterday a
Yazidi woman was recently freed from 12
years of captivity, ISIS captivity just
like last week.
Imagine what what what she went through.
So this is all the consequence of the
American intervention
wherever they intervene. So yeah and and
what happens is that when when a US ally
will will perpetrate all kinds of
atrocities on on helpless people the
western media will stay quiet about this
so no one comes to know right absolute
barbarity absolute hypocrisy that's
that's the kind of regime change the
west has been advocating for whenever
the the west does regime change they
give freedom to their new asset the new
puppet dictator to do whatever he wants.
It's a reward.
And the and what they expect in exchange
is that he will do whatever the west
tells tells him to do. He will not stray
from his path. As long as he will obey
the orders of the west, he's allowed to
do whatever he wants. That's how it
goes. And that's what we are seeing in
Syria.
Prash Prasam Sony says, "How to raise
standard of questions for you guys?" I
don't know.
I don't know man. I don't know. Ask ask
whatever comes to your mind and I'll try
and answer.
Okay. Lakshmanasan says, "What with with
major advances in drones, robotics, uh
military technology, Turkey is expanding
its influence across the Middle East and
Europe. Could this mark the beginning of
a neootoman geopolitical revival in the
region?
So Turkey is this strange
nation. Strange. Why do I say strange
nation? On the one hand, it has imperial
ambitions. On the other hand, it is not
fully sovereign. It's a member of NATO.
Let's let's see this. Okay, let's Google
this.
See how many US
nuclear weapons weapons
in Turkey.
There are an estimated 20 US nuclear
weapons B61 gravity bombs stored at
Inurik air base in Turkey.
These weapons are part of a larger
stockpile of US nuclear weapons deployed
in blah blah blah all that they're
stored in hardened b hardened bunkers
and protected by electronic systems and
US troops.
How many US military bases
bases in Turkey?
There are at least two known US military
installations in Turkey. Inik air base
and Ismir air station. Further there is
the Cucherik radar station and an Ankara
support facility
and in Churlik obviously you have US
nuclear weapons there and so on and so
forth. So Turkey is a nation that is not
territorially or militarily sovereign
because it has US military bases on its
soil which automatically makes it a
non-s sovereign nation and if it's a
part of NATO NATO it means that its
armed forces can come under the control
of a foreign citizen at least some part
of its armed forces will have to be
commanded by a foreign citizen which
means it's not fully militarily
sovereign either. So you have that okay
you have that Turkey is not fully
sovereign
but it has imperial ambitions. So if you
look at the geographical location of
Turkey it's Turkey you could say has a
god-gifted geographical location. It it
controls two of the most vital tro
points in the Mediterranean region.
First of all the strait of the Dardanels
over here. Yeah this one. Then you have
the sea of Marmara and then you have the
Bosphorus strait. Two extremely vital
geopolitical choke points
and Turkey sits on top of these two
choke points and by doing so it has been
rent seeking for the past 70 80 years
and that's why it's so important for
NATO. So Turkey is not fully sovereign.
It's a very important strategic location
and uh it has imperial ambitions and it
is doing well when it comes to
technology. Yeah, they they are
developing drones. They're developing
fighter planes. The KHN the fifth
generation Khan fighter plane which is
still I think as far as I know it's
still a prototype. Uh I'm not even sure
if the prototype has flown but whatever.
Uh drones they have good drones
apparently. Well the Pakistanis used
Turkish drones and we know what happened
to those drones. Uh but maybe those are
export versions and maybe the Turkish
drones are good. Possibly we have to uh
keep that in mind and allow for that
possibility.
Uh and Turkey is expanding its influence
across the Middle East and Europe with
US permission of course uh not really
Europe that much but uh central Asia
they're trying to wipe Armenia off out
of the map of the world and they want to
create a pan corridor that connects
Turkey all the way to the various Turk
nations central Asian nations.
So all of this that taken together
military technology, drones, robotics,
geo geopolitical ambitions, all of that
does it mean that there could be the
beginning of a neo-toman geopolitical
revival in the region? Only if the US
allows it, only if the US allows it only
if it aligns with US geopolitical
objectives. Otherwise, there'll be no
neo-toman geopolitical revival. And uh
even if there's a Turkish geopolitical
revival, it will not be allowed to take
neo-toman dimensions or neo-toman
uh or neotoman flavor.
Yeah, it the Ottoman flavor will remain
symbolic at best because otherwise
that's a problem for the US. So yeah,
it's complicated but Turkey is a US
asset. It also is dying with Russia. It
is doing things that the US doesn't
like. For example, the purchase of the
S400 system which displeased the US and
which is why Turkey was not allowed to
remain part of the F-35 program which I
think is a good thing for Turkey
actually because the F-35 is a flying
trash can and so on. Yeah.
MK says, "How did Israel acquire nukes?"
Well, there are various stories. Uh how
did the world come to know that that
Israelis have nukes? There was um an
Israeli traitor. The Israelis considered
him to be traitor. His name was Bordeai
Vanunu and he later changed his name to
D David Crossman or something. He
converted to Christianity and he was in
prison because of what he did and so on.
The Israelis were able to abduct him
from Europe and bring him back to Israel
and imprison him and he's right now in
Israel. So that's how the world came to
know about the Israeli nuclear program
and there was an Israeli collaboration
with South Africa I believe if I yeah it
was with South Africa and somewhere in
the 1960s or '7s there was this bunch of
US satellites called the VA satellites
that caught an incident in the southern
Atlantic Ocean
or double flash incident the VA incident
those satellites actually physics story
here these The satellite these
satellites were put in orbit to to catch
such incidents double flash. So whenever
you have an atmospheric nuclear
explosion
that is a double flash event. There's an
initial very initial very rapid flash
and then there's a slower flash slower
buildup which is the second flash. So a
nuclear explosion atmospheric
explosion has two flashes. It's a double
flash incident. So the VA satellites
were put in orbit to detect atmospheric
nuclear tests that would be that the
whoever would do it would try to hide.
But these satellites ended up fi finding
all these weird flashes across the
cosmos and these turned out to be a new
phenomenon called gamma ray bursts and
that's still kind of a mystery to some
extent in physics today in co in
astrophysics but coming back to this
there was a va incident in which there
these satellites caught what looked like
a nuclear test in the south southern
Atlantic ocean a va incident
1979. Yes,
an unidentified double flash of light
detected by an American VA satellite and
it was most likely u an atomic test done
jointly by Israel and South Africa
carried out jointly by South Africa and
Israel. Now how did so that that's
that's an interesting story I can give
you. How did Israel acquire nukes?
Who was it France that transferred
technology? Was it the US that
transferred technology? I'm not very
clear about that but I suppose you can
look it up.
Okay. Godliness says we have at least 7
crore illegal aliens or geographical.
Yeah, I agree with you but this is not a
ge geopolitical question right now. Of
course, this is an question of internal
security but I will not take this today
because we're discussing geopolitics
today. Yeah, I agree. This this
catastrophe has to stop and I agree with
you. But beyond that, I'll not say
anything right now.
Uh Amisha says, "Is Trump making America
alone again?
Making America alone again? What's my
take?"
Well, America doesn't have a lot of
friends right now, right?
uh whichever nations were positively
warmly inclined toward towards the US,
they have all been alienated by Trump's
actions, haven't they?
Trump has been imposing these these
these tariffs,
pretty aggressive tariffs on US allies.
These are armwisting tactics. These are
bullying tactics. 50% tariffs on Brazil.
I mean, what the hell? This is a US
asset. It's a US vasal. It's a US ally.
The EU is a US asset, a US vasal.
And when you start treating your allies
like this,
it u whatever
whatever warmth those those nations had
towards you will evaporate. So they will
comply with your demands because they
are afraid of you because you are more
powerful. But you will see all kinds of
passive aggressive behavior after that.
So wherever possible they will not
cooperate with you. So yeah, Trump is I
mean recently you had the the leader of
Singapore saying that the world needs uh
you need a world minus one which is one
world minus America kind of trading
order right financial order. So
everyone's everyone is fed up with what
Trump is doing. Uh the Americans
they don't have a lot of friends right
now because of the actions they're
taking. So yeah, Trump is indeed making
America alone. They are the most
powerful nation. They have global power
production capabilities. They have
military bases across the world, which
is why the world has to do what they
say. But nobody will
cooperate beyond what's required with
the US. And yeah, that does indeed make
America kind of alone in the world right
now. So that's what Trump is doing. He's
not doing his nation a favor. is
destroying the the global order his
nation created over the past 70 80 years
is destroying it one single-handedly.
Maybe that's why he was he has been made
president. Maybe that's why the deep
state made Trump president because they
want the world order to be upended and
and a new order to be created. Maybe
that's his task. So he's doing a good
job of of carrying out the orders of the
deep state. Um but yeah, it's not doing
his nation any favors.
It's making his nation alone. So Trump
is indeed making America alone again
like you say.
Nili says in the 9/11 attacks terrorists
were most mostly Saudi Arabians. Still
the US maintained friendly relations
with Saudi Arabia. Why is that? Like oil
can be acquired by other Gulf nations.
So this is a mystery. I don't know the
answer.
Yeah, I don't know.
Saudi Arabia is indeed a US uh
protectorate, US vasal, US ally,
whatever you want to say. Um
and yeah, you see
there was a previous bombing of the
World Trade Center. The first bombing
happened in 199.
It was carried out by Ramsey Yusf or
something. Let's Google that. So that
that guy was a Pakistani.
Okay. Uh Ramsey Ramsey Yousef
a Pakistani convicted terrorist who was
one of the main perpet the 1993 World
Trade Center bombing. Is he alive? He's
alive. Yeah, he's he's just 57 years
old.
So this guy was a Pakistani.
He carried out the 1993 World Trade
Center bombing, the bombing of a
Philippine Airlines flight.
He was a co-conspirator in some other
Bojinka plot.
um and so on and so forth. He was trying
to set a bomb in a doll. Well, that's
how nice that is. And he was extradited
to the US. So this is a Pakistani
terrorist who conducted a terrorist
attack on the US. Well, why did the US
still maintain relations with Pakistan?
Friendly relations because Pakistan is
useful for the US and because the
Pakistani government cooperated with the
US and extradited this terrorist to the
US. Same similarly when the 9/11 attacks
happened and u it emerged that many of
these terrorists were from Saudi Arabia.
I suppose the government of Saudi Arabia
must have cooperated fully with the US.
So this was not a government sponsored
thing. It was just a few citizens who
did that. So and Saudi Arabia was is
still very useful to the US and why
would they give that up? So that's why
that's why
uh anonymous scientist says how actively
does Vatican City interfere in the
geopolitics of Christian countries? I'm
not really sure about that. Um
the Vatican,
see the Vatican,
if the Vatican is geopolitically
powerful, it it may be part of the deep
state that controls the US. But beyond
that, I don't really know about that.
Um, the Vatican historically was very
powerful. It was the most powerful
entity in Europe. It decided the fates
of kingdoms and empires. It decided who
a king could marry or divorce and it
could decide not to grant a divorce to a
king even if he wanted. It had so much
power.
Right? So, historically, it was super
powerful. today I'm sure it's not
entirely lost its power but whatever
power it may have may be hidden beyond
the below the surface so yeah this is
kind of a mystery and I'm not really
sure how it actively and to what extent
it interferes in the geopolitics of
Christian countries I'm not really sure
but yeah it does interfere in the
internal affairs of India for example
because in India if you are what some
Christian priests what are the higher
ranked Christian priests called those
padis
uh bishops, cardinals, I think those are
appointed by the Vatican
and they have actual power over their
parishes and whatnot in India or the
population in population which in my
opinion is is interference in the
internal affairs of India. The Chinese
don't allow this but we do. So yeah
there is they do have some power
actually.
Okay, VS says, "If Boeing is facing so
many quality issues, what possible
alternative alternate steps would the US
take to alter the NGAD F-47 program?
Also, could you name a few books
available on the military-industrial
complex?" Um, what's NGAD47?
Let's see. NAD 47. NAD
47.
The F47, a fifth sixth generation
fighter plane being developed under the
US Air Force's next generation air
dominance program. It's envisioned as a
blah blah blah blah blah blah um
significant undertaken. 20 billion
initial contract has been awarded to
Boeing and future cost will reach into
the hundreds of billions. Look, when
Boeing develops a fighter jet for the
United States,
it's done in a completely different
facility compared to where they're
manufacturing the civilian aircraft.
And I assure you when Boeing is
manufacturing, designing, developing and
eventually manufacturing
uh the F-47 or any military fighter
plane, the safety standards, quality
standards will be to totally different
from what they employ in the civilian
program.
Okay? When they are manufacturing Boeing
737s or whatever it is that the
manufacturer, that's a different story.
So it won't be the same factory. It
won't be the same operation. It'll be a
totally different thing and totally
different set of engineers.
So I assure you there'll be no issues,
no quality issues when it comes to the
fighter planes.
Books available on military-industrial
complex. I haven't read any books on the
military industrial complex. I don't
know.
Okay. Geopolitical Dubai says Turk
Turkish. Will you please marry me? I am
Muslim like you. We are one um our
ancestors are the same. I love you
Bangladesh next superpower. I have
absolutely no idea what you're saying
but all right
this is a geopolitics live stream sir
we'll talk about geopolitics here.
Kunus says even if India reaches 10 to15
trillion dollar economy and if resource
inequality persists and per capita
income stays near 3,000 won't wouldn't
it be pointless
even Nigeria may reach 5 6 to 7 trillion
what makes such growth meaningful then
see right now India is a 4.5 trillion
let's let's see this okay
um let's Google this quickly
what's India's current GDP India GDP
in
trillion
USD
how many trillion okay it's 4.2 trillion
dollar USD
it's 4.2 trillion USD right now okay and
GDP per capita
GDP per capita is 2,700 USD right now
more or less.
So our GDP is 4.2 trillion
and GDP per capita is 2.7,000.
So if we become of if we double our GDP
with the same population, our GDP per
capita will become
5.4,000.
it won't remain near 3,000.
Okay. If the GDP per cap GDP triples to
12.6
then the GDP per capita will become 2.7
* 3 21
8.1. So it won't remain near 3,000.
Please this is just basic mathematics.
So with a $15 trillion economy, our GDP
per capita will be closer to 10,000. It
will be above 9,000. It will be nowhere
near 3,000. How is it pointless?
How is it pointless?
Your population is not going to go
beyond 1.4 billion, right? Our
population is now slowly start going to
start declining.
So if we reach a $15 trillion economy,
our GDP per capita will be very close to
10,000,
not 3,000.
Please get the math right sir. So how is
it pointless? It's very pointful
actually. It'll be great. Your living
standards will increase significantly.
Quality of life will increase
significantly
and resource inequality.
I don't think there is resource in India
is one of the least in unequal countries
in the world. Recently the world bank
report a world bank report came out.
India is one of the least unequal
countries in the world. And show me any
country that is that has complete
equality.
Equality is unnatural.
Please get understand that you've been
fed this propaganda that everybody has
to be equal. How can everybody be equal?
Is everybody the same? Does everybody
have the same skills, same talent, same
IQ, same everything? No, you can't have
equality. You can give everybody equal
rights, but you can't have equal
outcomes. Some people are just naturally
better, more intelligent, more
hardworking, more consistent, more
disciplined. They will perform far
better than somebody who is lazy.
So how can you have equality?
So there's never going to be equality
and it is undesirable. If you impose
complete equality in a country, no
matter how intelligent, how hardworking
or or lazy a person is, then it is it
disincentivizes people from working
hard.
So we don't want equality. We want
equality
of rights, not equality of outcomes. And
India is one of the least unequal
countries in the world. So please don't
be brainwashed by whatever. Let's let's
find that World Bank report about
equality, right? Shall we?
India India
India
inequality
world bank
look at this according to the World Bank
India ranks fourth globally in income
equality
gen index of 25.5 indicating a
significantly low level of inequality
okay I don't know what propaganda you
have been fed my dear viewers Many of
you
India is among the top four most equal
countries globally. Please get that
there's a tremendous amount of negative
propaganda about India. But the World
Bank itself has put out this data which
shows that India is among the top four
most equal nations. Now what more do you
want?
So first of all there is this myth of
income of resource and whatever
inequality is an absolute myth. It's a
lie. It's propaganda. Secondly, when we
reach a $15 trillion trillion dollar
economy, our GDP per capita will be
around $10,000,
not $3,000.
Okay? So, please get your facts right,
gentlemen. Okay.
MK says, "Why is Russia not focusing on
cuttingedge technology like AI chip
fabrication, quantum computing, etc.?"
Uh the Russians do have a semiconductor
program. I'm not sure to what extent it
is it has succeeded or not. I think they
are working on it. AI I think Russ I'm
I'm not sure what Russia is doing about
AI.
One doesn't hear of any any major
Russian LLMs
and if they are indeed developing AI
systems maybe they're doing it in secret
or maybe they're not doing it at all.
But if they don't do it, they obviously
will be left behind which will be a
tremendous problem for Russia. So I'm
not sure what the deal is. Uh quantum
computing once again I'm not sure. So if
they are if they are pursuing these
technologies de you know development of
these technologies it's it's probably
being done in secret and if it's not
being done at all then Russia risks
being completely left behind even behind
countries like India because India is
now taking things seriously India is
taking quantum computing seriously
definitely in the the past year or so uh
AI we are now waking up to AI and the
chip fabrication. Absolutely. We're
taking it extremely seriously. If Russia
is not doing it, then it risks being
very quickly left behind and right now
it there's nothing in the public domain
about what Russia is doing. So yeah,
it's kind of kind of unknown what Russia
is doing about this.
Okay. Divor Singh says India is not a
hegemonic state, but if we go grow to 10
trillion dollars, countries that don't
play by the rules like China will defeat
us again. or should we not play by the
rules to win? Okay. Yeah, we are not a
hgemonic state. We have historically
never been a hegemonic state. No matter
how powerful our emperors have been,
they have never really sought to,
you know, play the hgemonic game and and
colonize other countries and cultures
and all that. It's never been the case.
It's not part of our culture. So, you
are absolutely right. Now today we are
in the 21st century and we know how what
what the rules of of the game are right.
Um
so if we if we let's say become a 105
trillion dollar economy but we still
play the same old defensive game and
don't play the hegemonic game then
nations that do play the hgemonic game
will have an advantage over us. Right?
So the point is this, who makes the
rules?
The strong make the rules
and the weak must suffer by the rules
that the strong make. So the rules can
be changed at will. If you are strong,
you can make your own rules.
So for until recently, India could not
even imagine
walking away unilaterally from something
like the Indust treaty. But today we
have done that visa v Pakistan.
A few years ago, China walked away
unilaterally from its agreement, from
its treaty with the UK about Hong Kong,
one nation, two systems. China said no
more. We no longer recognize this
treaty. China is way more powerful.
And that's why they were able to do
that. The US can unilaterally walk away
at will from any treaty. Example, JCPOA,
a joint comprehensive power plan of
action, which Trump walked away from.
this treaty that was signed between the
US and Iran, Trump just walked away from
it. So the more powerful you become, the
more you can bend the rules or create
new rules. So I suspect that as India
gets grows gets more powerful, India
will also play the same game. And if we
don't do that, well then somebody else
will make the rules that we have to play
by. Um
so it's not like we should not play by
the rules. It's it's more like we should
define the rules that we play by and I
think we are definitely showing
indications of of doing that. I mean
walking away from the industry is
exactly that that we are no longer going
to play by the old rule book. We're
going to make new rules now and we will
play by those rules. So we are doing
that and that's a great indication
that's a that's that's a great sign that
India is no longer that that idealistic
nation that historically we have been we
will play by the old rules we will not
fight at night but the enemies will
fight at night right prora Johan
unfortunately Pritara Johan he was a
great man great king but he lost and if
you lose you're going to be the butt of
ridicule no matter how great you were
but if you make one mistake and you lose
then you're going to be the butt of
ridicule for the rest of history
unfortunately. So he's in that
unfortunate position. Anyhow, Dnur Singh
says, "Is America too big to fail?"
Nobody is too big to fail. I mean,
imagine the Roman Empire at its at at
its peak. It was too big to fail, wasn't
it? And yet it failed spectacularly in a
very short time comp relatively short
time. Just a couple of centuries.
Right? I mean, something that happened
in 10 AD ended up slowly but steadily
triggering the decline of the Roman
Empire. The Roman Empire actually grew
to its might after what happened in 10
AD. Um, what is it called? The battle of
Tutubber forest. But u anyhow so nothing
no empire is too big to fail and it's
just a historical certainty that empires
come into existence they they rise they
grow to their pinnacle and then
something happens and they fall it's
just a historical certainty every empire
fails eventually so America is not big
too big to fail I think the bigger you
are the more likely you are to fail
because you become complacent you
So yeah, that's the deal. All right, my
friends, I am done with uh geopolitical
doas. The USSR failed. Another example.
There you have it. Nobody imagined the
USSR would fail, but there we have it.
The USSR also failed.
Okay, so we are at the end of today's
live stream. Thank you so much for all
the questions. It was great fun taking
the questions, answering them all. And
uh yeah, that's it for today. Thank you
so much and I look forward to seeing you
in next week's live streams. So thank
you very much. Take care. Keep asking
questions. Keep raising your standards.
Keep learning and I will see you next
week. Thank you very much. Take care.